Hi welcome to this week's video. Today
嗨！欢迎來到本周的视频。 今天
we're going to talk about array formulas. And we have a brand new
我们要说说数组公式 。 我们有一个全新的
example to work with array formulas. In this week's example
例子来演示数组公式 。 在本周的例子中
we are a teacher. And that's a nice coincidence, because of course
我们扮演一名教师。 而这是个很棒的巧合，当然是因为
I'm a teacher and this is actually quite a real-life experience
我是一名教师，这实际上是一个
of how I analyze exam results. So let's have a look at the spreadsheet that
我如何分析考试成绩的真实经验。 因此，让我们在本周的视频
we're going to work with
看看我们要处理的电子表格。
in this week's videos. It is about a bunch of students
它与在我的班上的一群同学
that are in my class. I have their student numbers, their names
有关。 我有他们的学号，名字
and the year in which they have started.
和入学年份。
The names, then the ID's and the year that they started their studies.
姓名，ID和他们开始入学的年份。
And in addition to that, I have exam results, so you see I have a number of
除此之外，我有考试结果，所以你看到
questions,
我有许多疑问，
I have a list of students and then for all of the questions I have
我有学生名单，然后我的问题是
the perfect score and the score for all of the students. And you might think that I
我有满分分数和与所有学生的分数。 你可能认为我
would use this
会用这个
spreadsheet just to analyze the marks for the students,
电子表格来为学生分析分数，
but that's not true. I also use the exam results as a means
但事实并非如此。 我也用考试结果作为
to analyze the quality of the exam. So I have a look at the results
分析考试质量的方法。 所以我在看结果也
and I look at what question actually impacts
看哪个问题
the scores of the exams most. Let me give you an example of that.
最影响考试分数。 让我给你举一个例子。
So if I look at this spreadsheet, I see that those questions 1 and 2,
从电子表格可以看出，问题1和2的
the answers are pretty similar. In many cases the same score is given
答案是非常相似的。 在许多情况下，会有相同的分数
or a very similar score. So if I want to dig into that what I could do of
或非常相似分数。 所以，如果我想深入探讨，
course, is take the SUM()
我当然是使用SUM（）
of all the scores for one question and take the SUM()
计算这一个问题的所有分数
for all the scores of the other question and compare those two together. And I can
和SUM（）计算另一问题的所有分数，然后互相比较。 我可以
see
看到
that indeed the difference isn't that big between question 1 and 2.
确实问题1和2之间的差别并不是那么大。
However that is a bit misleading,
不过就是有点误导性，
because you see in this if I would just SUM() these cells
因为你看这，如果我只对这些单元格使用SUM()函数
the sums would be the same, yet the answers would be very different.
总和将是相同的，但是答案将是非常不同的。
So the SUM() is not a good solution to really understand
因此，SUM()并不是一个真正了解
how these two questions differ from each other. So what to do?
这两个问题有何不同的好办法。 那么怎么办？
What I actually wanted to do, is take the difference between
我其实想做的是
all of the cells between all of the results for those two questions.
在这两个问题的所有单元格、所有结果中找出不同来。
Let me do that and unfortunately, double clicking now doesn't work,
让我这样试一试，不幸的是，双击现在不起作用了，
Because there's an empty column so have to really drag
因为有一个空白列，所以我得把
the formula down and then I can see the differences between all the cells.
公式拖下来，然后我就可以看到 所有的单元格之间的差值。
But as you can see, some differences are positive and others are negative,
但正如你所看到的，有些差值是正的，有些是负的，
so we need to take the absolute value of the difference
因此，我们需要对差值取绝对值
in order to get the real difference between
以得到这两个问题之间的
the two questions. So we drag
真正的差值。 于是我们把
the absolute difference down and now we can see:
绝对差值拖下来，现在我们可以看到：
hey is there really a difference? If we sum these values together
哎，是真的有区别吗？ 如果我们这些值加在一起
we see that the difference is indeed between these two questions, is
我们看到这两个问题之间的差异确实存在，
not that big. The difference is 21
且没有那么大。 总差值是21，
and we have 14 students so that's about 1.5 points
而我们有14个学生，所以在那些问题中，每个学生的差值
per student difference between those questions. This helps me,
大约是1.5。 这帮到了我，
this help me with the analysis because now I know how these two questions
这帮助我分析，因为 现在我知道这两个问题
relate to each other. However I don't have two questions, I have 12.
的相互关系。 不过，如果我不只有2个问题，而是12个。
So if I would want to repeat this analysis for all of them
所以，如果我想重复这个来分析所有问题
I would have to make a lot of auxilliary columns, here you see it,
我得添加很多的辅助列，你看，
there's no end to it almost. That's not what I want.
几乎没有尽头。 这并不是我想要的。
I hope you remember from previous lessons that duplication
我希望你从之前的课上记住，复制
is not a good thing. If you're doing the same thing over and over, if you're
并不是一件好事。 如果你正在一遍又一遍地做同样的事情，如果你正在
making a lot of columns,
添加很多相似的列，
or a lot of rows, that are very similar you have to think of me. Please think of me and think:
或者很多相似的行，你得想起我。 请你想起我，并想到：
"Oh no duplication! No good, I have to go back to the MOOC
“哦，不能复制！ 复制不好，我得回到MOOC
and look at a smarter way to do this." So
去寻找一个更聪明的方式来做这件事。” 所以
how to this smart. Let me first remove all those duplicate columns
怎么样才是聪明的呢？ 让我先删除所有这些重复列
we don't want them, we zoom out a little bit
我们不要这些，我们缩小了一点
and we also remove this, because we're going to do this in a more compact,
同时我们还要拿掉这个东西，因为我们准备以一个更紧凑，
in a smarter way. So what we would like to do
更聪明的方式来做这件事。 所以，我们想要做的事情
is, at once subtract
是，一次性
question 1 from question 2 without all those
从问题2中减去问题1 而不要所有这些
intermediate steps. So this is a good attempt, we just subtract
中间步骤。 所以这是一个很好的 尝试，我们只是
a range from another range. And let's see with the evaluate function
从另一范围扣除一个范围。 让我们来看看有了evaluate函数
what exactly happened here now. We have the first column, if we evaluate it
現在这里究竟发生了什么。 我们有第一栏，如果我们evaluate它
we get 8, which is the first item
我们得到8，这是第一栏
of the column. And this is because what Excel now calculates is the intersection,
的项目。 这是因为 Excel现在计算的是交集，
we talked about that in previous lessons.
这个我们在前面的课程中谈过。
So this is close to what we want but not exactly what we want. We don't want Excel
因此这已经接近了我们想要的，但又不完全是我们想要的那样。 我们不需要Excel
to calculate the intersection immediately,
立刻计算交点，
what we want to have is all of the differences.
我们想要的是所有的差值
And this is, you can guess this probably
而这个，你可能已经猜到这了
where array formulas come in, because Excel can evaluate this function
正是数组公式进来的地方，因为 Excel可以以两种不同的方式
in two different ways. Let me show you how
评估这个函数。 让我告诉你另外一种
the alternatives look like. So this is sort of the normal
方式是什么样子的。 刚刚这个可以说是标准，
value, the normal way of doing it is what we just did.
标准做法就是我们刚才做的 那样。
We paste this formula in
我们将此公式粘贴
and now the alternative way, the array way of doing it,
进去，而现在的另一种方式，即做这件事的数组方式，
we don't hit enter, we hit control shift enter.
我们不按回车，而是按control、shift和回车。
And if we do that we get this nice curly braces
如果我们这样做，我们不过得到了公式周围的一个漂亮的大括号
around for the formula and this is
这
not good in the sense, because we got the same
其实没什么意义，因为我们得到了同样的
result. So you might think there's no difference, the curly braces
结果。 所以你可能会觉得没有什么 差别，大括号并
don't do anything. However the way it's calculated,
不能做任何事。 然而计算的方式，
is really really different. What's underneath
真的已经不同了。 底下的东西
is different. And in order for us to understand the difference between those two
已经不同了。 而为了让我们理解这两之间的区别
ways of calculation, we need to use type theory.
两个计算方法之间的区别，我们需要使用类型理论。
In the first version, in the normal version,
在减函数的第一版，普通版本中，
of the minus function, this is what happens: We have the range
会发生如下情况：我们有范围
B3 to B16
B3到B16
and we subtract from that the range
然后我们从中减去范围
C3 to C16.
C3到C16。
So what happens here is the reduction,
这里会发生的是减法，
the intersection between the two ranges. This is what Excel
该两个范围的交集。 这是Excel所
returns for a range, so this is
回传的范围，
8, the first intersection
所以这是8，第一个交集減去10，
minus 10, the second intersection
第二交集
which results
的结果是
in -2, that's what we have seen. So what happens
在-2，这就是我们所看到的。 所以
in the alternative version, the curly braces, the
替代版本大括號、array版本發生了什麼，
It looks
它看起来
exactly the same, but what happens inside is really really different.
完全一样，但是里面真的很不同。
So in this version, again
所以，在这个方案中，再次从
B3 to B16 minus
B3到B16减去
C3 to C16.
C3到C16。
In the array version,
在数组方案中，
no reduction takes place. Excel calculates this subtraction
没有减法发生。 Excel在整个范围内
on the entire range. So internally
计算减法。 所以在内部
we have B3 minus C3
我们有B3减C3
and then B4
然后B4
minus C4 and then B5
减去C4，然后B5
minus C5
减去C5，
and I guess you can come up with the rest.
我想你能想到剩下的情况。
And then all of this, the subtractions
然后所有这些，都进行了
are calculated, all of them. So we get the list,
减法计算，全部。 所以我们得到的列表中，
with, 8 minus 10, 0 minus 0
就有8减10，0减0，
5 minus 5, etc.
5减去5等
So the result
所以
of this array, of this curly braces version
这个数组，这个大括号版的，公式的结果，
of the formula is a list
是一个列表
2, 0, 0 etc.
2，0，0等
But because there's no room for Excel to plot this entire list,
但因为Excel没有绘制整张列表的空间，
we only have one cell, we only get the first
我们仅有一个单元格，我们只得到了
number in the list.
列表中的第一个数。
But that doesn't mean that the result is a number
但是，这并不表示结果是数字
the result is actually a list. It looks the same
其结果实际上是一个列表。 它看起来相同
but internally it's really really different. So let's go back
但在本质上它是 不同的。 因此，让我们回去，
and see how this looks in Excell. We don't need the glasses anymore.
看看这在Excell会如何。 我们再也不需要眼镜了。
So if we look
因此，如果我们看
in our spreadsheet, we see no difference.
我们的电子表格 ，我们没有看到区别。
However internally it's really really different. The first version
但是在本质上是不同的。 第一个版本
results in a number and the second version results in a list.
结果是一个数和第二 版本的结果是列表。
So what can we do with the list? It is really nice that we have a list now, but what to do?
因此，我们可以使用列表做什么？ 我们有一个列表真的很棒，但是要做什么？
How to show and work with this list? So the first thing we can do with an array
如何显示与使用列表來工作？ 因此，第一件我们可以用
formula,
array函数做的事情，
is give it space. Make room in the spreadsheet for Excel
就是给它的空间。 在电子表格上腾出空间让Excel
not to plot the first number only, but to plot the entire resulting array.
不是只绘第一栏的图，而是对 整个array的结果绘图。
So let's have a look at how that looks like. So we're going to remove the normal
因此，让我们来看看这会如何。 所以我们要删除正常
version
版本
and the array version so you can really see the difference.
和array版本，所以你可以真正地看到差别。
We throw them away. In the normal version
我们把它们舍弃。 在普通版本
if we make room for the entire array
如果我们腾出空间给整个阵列
we put in a normal formula, nothing happens. We only get
我们放入正常的公式，没有任何反应。 我们只得到
one result. But for the array version, if we make room, if we give it space
一个结果。 但对于该array版本，如果 我们腾出空间，如果我们给它的空间
and then we hit shift control enter, what happens is we get
然后我们敲敲shift control enter键， 发生的事情是，我们得到
the entire resulting array. And now you see the list that we had on the
整个结果数组。 现在你看到我们在黑板上
blackboard.
的列表。
We have it now in a spreadsheet, because we gave Excel room
我们现在在电子表格有一个列表，因为 我们给了Excel空间
to show: I have this and I have this array of data
来显示：我有列表，我有这个数组的数据给你，
to give you and not just the first. For an alternative,
而不是只是第一個版本的。 另一种选择方式，
what we can do with an array formula is flatten the list.
我们可以利用array公式来扁平化列表。
Making this entire list into one value
通过增加一个函数，使得整个列表成为一个值。
by adding a function around it. So we have a list
因此，我们有一个列表
and what we can tell Excel is do something with that list.
我们可以告诉Excel用列表做些事情。
For instance SUM() the list, so
例如SUM（）的列表中，
in a normal version if we would SUM() the intersection of two
在正常的版本，如果我们 对两个范围的交集用
ranges
SUM（）
we just get -2, because the result is -2. We can add a SUM() around it, but it
我们就得到-2，因为结果是 -2。 我们在周围添加SUM（），但它
will still be -2.
仍然会是-2。
In the array version we get a different result. Look at how that looks like,
在数组版本中，我们得到了不同的 结果。 看看結果如何，
If we enter the SUM() around the array
如果我们在数组版本的公式 输入SUM（）
version of the formula, then we get -5.
然后我们得到-5。
Because what happens now is the SUM()
因为现在SUM（）函数
has been calculated over this
已经计算出了这个
entire list that has resulted from the array formula.
由数组公式产生的整个列表。
And here you see the comparison with all the separate subtractions
在这里，你看到了所有的单独的减法的对照组
and if we add a SUM() around that we get the exact same value.
如果我们添加一个SUM（），我们得到了完全相同的值。
So this, all the separate subtraction and a SUM(),
所以所有的独立差集和 SUM（）
result in the exact same thing as an array formula with a SUM() around it.
导致的结果与数组公式周围的SUM（）的结果一样。
And in this way, this is how we can solve our original problem
而这方法，是我們如何解决最初
of wanting to compare all the questions with each other.
想对所有问题做相互比较的这个疑问。
We don't need an auxiliary column and a SUM(),
我们并不需要一个辅柱栏和 一个SUM（）
we can calculate the entire sum in one cell,
我们可以在一个单元格计算整个总和，
and this saves us a lot of space. Let's see how that looks like.
这为我们节省了大量的空间。 让我们看看結果如何。
We don't need that anymore,
我们不再需要SUM（）与辅柱栏了，
and we can use it now to calculate the difference between question 1
我们现在可以用它来只在一个单元格内计算问题1和问题2
and question 2, in one cell only. So we take the SUM()
之间的区别。 我们用SUM（）函数计算
of the entire range, the entire B-range
整个范围，B区
minus the entire C-range, where we need the absolute
减去C区，再取绝对值
as we did in the beginning, and then control shift enter
就像我们在一开始做的，然后 按shift回车
gives us the result of 21 just as we had in the beginning.
就像我们一开始一样得到了21的结果。
So with the use of array formulas, we have reduced
用了数组公式，我们仅用了一个单元格就减掉
a column and a SUM() to one cell only.
一列和一个SUM()函数。
That's the power of array formulas.
这就是数组公式 的好处。